<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) >
<!ATTLIST xi:include
    xmlns:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href       CDATA      #REQUIRED
    parse      (xml|text) "xml"
    encoding   CDATA      #IMPLIED >
<!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY>
<!ATTLIST xi:fallback
    xmlsn:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
<!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include">
<!ENTITY % local.section.class "| xi:include">
]>

<!-- FILE        : Augusta.xml
     SUBJECT     : Master document for the Augusta documentation set.
     AUTHOR      : (C) Copyright 2014 by Peter C. Chapin <PChapin@vtc.vsc.edu>

This is the documentation for the Augusta Ada compiler. -->

<book status="draft">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Augusta</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Chapin</surname>
      <othername role="mi">C.</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Vermont Technical College</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Computer Information Systems Department</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2014</year>
      <holder>Peter C. Chapin</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
        terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
        by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES,
        with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. A copy
        of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <!-- Do we really want to include this revision history now? -->
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>2020-12-31</date>
        <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
        <revremark>This is a work in progress. Release 1.0 is scheduled for the end of
          2020.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Augusta is an open source Ada compiler developed as a personal project by me, Peter C.
      Chapin. As a person interested in Ada related technologies, I created Augusta primarily
      for my own education and enjoyment. However, it is also my hope that Augusta will
      eventually provide another option besides GNAT for those interested in using an open
      source Ada compiler. Although GNAT is a fine product, I believe in the value of diversity
      when it comes to available programming tools.</para>

    <para>Augusta is a long term project. Since I can only work on it in my spare time and since
      I'm not expecting many contributors at first, I anticipate it taking years before Augusta
      reaches any level of maturity. Yet to put a concrete time line on my work I have decided
      to release version 1.0 of Augusta on December 31, 2020. At that time I intend to have a
      usable compiler ready, for some reasonable definition of "usable."</para>

    <para>Augusta is written primarily in the Scala programming language. I chose Scala because
      it is a functional language, and thus supports features that I believe will be helpful for
      compiler construction (such as algebraic data types and pattern matching). Accordingly I
      intend to write Augusta in as purely a functional style as feasible with the hope that
      doing so will make the code more understandable, more reliable, and more amenable to
      parallelization. In addition Scala gives me access to an enormous collection of Java
      libraries, tools, and technologies, many of which are very powerful and highly mature. I
      intend to capitalize on that legacy as much as possible during the development of
      Augusta.</para>

    <para>I understand that Scala is an unusual choice as an implementation language for an Ada
      compiler. I understand that I would be more likely to attract help from the Ada community
      if I wrote Augusta in Ada. However, as a personal project I have the luxury of selecting
      tools that interest me even if they might not be strategically optimal. I hope my choice
      of Scala pays off in the long run. If the compiler is easier to write or if Augusta
      eventually becomes a bridge between the Scala/Java and Ada communities, my choice might
      prove to be strategic after all.</para>

    <para>August targets the LLVM compiler framework. This allows me to defer the details of low
      level code generation and optimization to the framework. Thus in theory Augusta supports
      all target architectures supported by LLVM, both now and in the future. This approach also
      allows me to capitalize on future advances made in LLVM technology. However, unlike high
      level virtual machines such as the JVM or CLR, LLVM should not restrict my implementation
      options. I believe it will be easier to accurately implement a language like Ada, which is
      intended to support low level programming, on top of a low level framework.</para>

    <para>I anticipate that as Augusta matures others will become attracted to the project and
      may join the effort. For this reason, aside from this introduction, the documentation is
      written as if it is being authored by a group of contributors rather than just a single
      person. This will reduce the amount of editing needed when there actually is a group of
      Augusta contributors!</para>

    <para>Although I hope others will become interested in this project in the future, I am also
      realistic enough to know that I will most likely be the only contributor for some time.
      People don't want to spend time on a grand project that just fizzles out in a couple of
      months. I will need to prove Augusta's seriousness by demonstrating a sustained effort and
      steady progress before anyone is likely to be willing to invest in it. This actually suits
      me fine because it allows me to shape the design and structure of the project on my own
      before others with competing views start to participate.</para>

    <para>This documentation describes both the design and use of the Augusta compiler.</para>

    <!-- Include disclaimer. -->

  </preface>

  <xi:include href="Vision.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Build.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="User.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Requirements.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Design.xml"/>

  <!-- <bibliography> ... </bibliography> -->

</book>
