<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
  
<chapter id="Vision">
  <title>Augusta Vision Statement</title>

  <para>In this section we outline the philosophy and long range goals of Augusta. By doing so
    we put Augusta in context and sketch an overall vision for the project. The vision is
    intended to guide the project's development and be the source of its requirements.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should be constructed in a modular fashion so that it can be effectively
        called as a library from other applications. Augusta should support developers of Ada
        tools by exposing independent components, such as the parser and type checker, as well
        defined modules with clean, documented interfaces.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should support being used from modern IDEs using whatever means and
        protocols are appropriate to do so.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should support ASIS.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should support an extension architecture so that users can extend the
        compiler in useful ways in a well defined manner.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should be designed from the ground up to take advantage of modern hardware
        by using parallelism and distributed computing when appropriate.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should be a "compiler writer's compiler," optionally exposing various
        compiler internals that might of interest to the power user.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should attempt to be compatible enough with GNAT so that one could easily
        port a GNAT project to Augusta. On the other hand Augusta shouldn't be slavishly
        compatible with GNAT and should develop its own approach to doing things where
        appropriate.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Augusta should attempt to integrate the Ada, Scala, and LLVM communities. It should,
        to the greatest extent possible, follow the best practices of all these communities and
        attempt to create a "comfortable common ground" for potential contributors from these
        communities.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</chapter>
